I think we have to do something
اعتقد اننا لابد من فعل شئ
about a piece of the culture of medicine that has to change.
عن جزء الثقافة الطبية التي تحتاج لتغير
And I think it starts with one physician, and that's me.
واعتقد انها ستبدأ بطبيب واحد, وهو انا
And maybe I've been around long enough
وربما انني تواجدت هنا لفترة طويلة لما فيه الكفاية
that I can afford to give away some of my false prestige
لانني اتحمل التخلي عن بعض من هيبتي الكاذبة
Before I actually begin the meat of my talk,
وقبل ان ابدأ في لحم الكلام
let's begin with a bit of baseball.
لنبدأ بقليل من البيسبول
Hey, why not?
مهلاً, لما لا؟
We're near the end, we're getting close to the World Series.
نحن على وشك النهاية, قاربنا على الوصول الى نهاية مسلسل الحياة
We all love baseball, don't we?
كلنا نحب البيسبول, صح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Baseball is filled with some amazing statistics.
البيسبول تمتلئ بأحصائيات مذهلة
And there's hundreds of them.
ويوجد منها المئات
"Moneyball" is about to come out, and it's all about statistics
"موني بول" على وشك ان يأتي وكل ما يهم هي الإحصائيات
and using statistics to build a great baseball team.
واستعمال الاحصائيات لبناء فريق بيسبول عظيم.
that I hope a lot of you have heard of.
وأملي ان يكون عدد كبير منكم سمع عنها.
It's called batting average.
تُدعى الضرب المتوسط
So we talk about a 300, a batter who bats 300.
لذلك نحن نتحدث عن 300, الضارب الذي ضرب 300
That means that ballplayer batted safely, hit safely
هذا يعني أن لاعب الكره ضرب بأمان، وضرب بسلام
three times out of 10 at bats.
ثلاث مرات من 10, في المضرب.
That means hit the ball into the outfield,
وهذا يعني ضرب الكرة في ارض الملعب,
it dropped, it didn't get caught,
سقطت, لم يتم التقاطها,
and whoever tried to throw it to first base didn't get there in time
والشخص الذي حاول رميها للقاعدة الاولى لم يصل الى هناك في الوقت المناسب
and the runner was safe.
وكان العدَاء في امان.
Three times out of 10.
ثلاثة مرات من 10.
Do you know what they call a 300 hitter
هل تعرف ماذا يسمون الذي يضرب 300
in Major League Baseball?
في دوري البيسبول؟
Good, really good,
جيد, جيد جداً,
maybe an all-star.
ربما نجماً للجميع.
Do you know what they call
هل تعرف ماذا يسمون
a 400 baseball hitter?
الذي يضرب 400 كرة بيسبول؟
That's somebody who hit, by the way,
بالمناسبة ذلك شخصاً يضرب,
four times safely out of every 10.
أربع مرات بسلام من بين كل 10.
Legendary --
أسطوري --
as in Ted Williams legendary --
كما هو في تيد وليامز الأسطوري --
the last Major League Baseball player
اخر لاعب في دوري
to hit over 400 during a regular season.
يضرب اكثر من 400 خلال موسم عادي.
Now let's take this back into my world of medicine
الان دعونا نرجع الى عالم الطب.
where I'm a lot more comfortable,
حيث اكون اكثر ارتياحاً,
or perhaps a bit less comfortable
او ربما اقل بقليل من الارتياح
after what I'm going to talk to you about.
بعد الذي سأتحدث عنه.
Suppose you have appendicitis
افترض ان لديك التهاب الزائدة الدودية
and you're referred to a surgeon
وتم تحويلك الى جراح
who's batting 400 on appendectomies.
الذي ضرب 400 في الزائدة الدودية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Somehow this isn't working out, is it?
بطريقة او باخرى هذا لا يصلح, صحيح؟
Now suppose you live
الان نفترض انك عشت
in a certain part of a certain remote place
في جزء معين في مكان بعيد
and you have a loved one
ولديك محبوب
who has blockages in two coronary arteries
لديه انسداد في اثنتين من الشرايين التاجية
and your family doctor refers that loved one to a cardiologist
وحوّل طبيب أسرتك محبوبك الى طبيب القلب
who's batting 200 on angioplasties.
الذي ضرب 200 في قسطرة القلب.
But, but, you know what?
ولكن, ولكن, تعرف ماذا؟
She's doing a lot better this year. She's on the comeback trail.
تحسنت كثيراً هذا العام, وهي الان في طريق استرداد عافيتها.
And she's hitting a 257.
وهي تصل 257.
Somehow this isn't working.
بطريقة او بأخرى هذا لا يصلح.
But I'm going to ask you a question.
لكني سوف اسأل سؤالا
What do you think a batting average
ما هو متوسط الضرب
for a cardiac surgeon or a nurse practitioner
لجراح القلب او الممرضة
or an orthopedic surgeon,
او جراح العظام,
an OBGYN, a paramedic
طبيب النساء والتوليد, مسعف
is supposed to be?
يفترض ان يكون؟
1,000, very good.
1,000, جيد جداً.
Now truth of the matter is,
الان حقيقة الامر هي,
nobody knows in all of medicine
لا احد يعرف كل الطب
what a good surgeon
ياله من جراح جيد
or physician or paramedic
او طبيب او مسعف
is supposed to bat.
يفترض ان يضرب.
What we do though is we send each one of them, including myself,
مانفعله هو اننا نرسل كل واحد منهم, الى من فيهم انا,
out into the world
الى العالم الخارجي
with the admonition, be perfect.
مع التذكير, كن مثالياً.
Never ever, ever make a mistake,
لا ترتكب نهائياً, ابداً, ابداً أي خطأً,
but you worry about the details, about how that's going to happen.
ولكنك تقلق من التفاصيل, عن كيفما سيحدث ذلك.
And that was the message that I absorbed
وكانت تلك هي الرسالة التي استوعبتها.
when I was in med school.
عندما كنت في كلية الطب.
I was an obsessive compulsive student.
كنت طالباً استحواذي وقهري.
In high school, a classmate once said
مرة في الثانوية احد الزملاء قال
that Brian Goldman would study for a blood test.
ان برايان قولدمان سيدرس فحص الدم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And so I did.
وهكذا فعلت.
And I studied in my little garret
ودرست في غرفتي العلية
at the nurses' residence at Toronto General Hospital,
في مقر الممرضات في مستشفى تورنتو العام، (Toronto General Hospital)
And I memorized everything.
حفظت كل شيء.
I memorized in my anatomy class
حفظت في صف علم التشريح
the origins and exertions of every muscle,
الاصول والاجهاد من كل عضلة,
every branch of every artery that came off the aorta,
كل فرع من فروع الشريان الذي يأتي من الشريان الأورطي,
differential diagnoses obscure and common.
تشخيصات تفريقية غامضة ومشتركة.
I even knew the differential diagnosis
حتى انني عرفت التشخيص التفريقي
in how to classify renal tubular acidosis.
في كيفية تصنيف الحماض الأنبوبي الكلوي.
And all the while,
طوال الوقت,
I was amassing more and more knowledge.
كنت اجمع المزيد والمزيد من المعرفة.
And I did well, I graduated with honors,
كنت حسن, تخرجت بمرتبة الشرف،
cum laude.
بامتياز.
And I came out of medical school
وتخرجت من كلية الطب
with the impression
بانطباع
that if I memorized everything and knew everything,
انني قمت بحفظ كل شيء وعرفت كل شيء,
or as much as possible,
او بقدر المستطاع,
as close to everything as possible,
قريب من كل شيء ممكن,
that it would immunize me against making mistakes.
انها ستحصنني من ارتكاب الاخطاء.
And it worked
ونجحت
for a while,
لوقت من الزمن,
until I met Mrs. Drucker.
الى ان التقيت بالسيدة دراكر.
I was a resident at a teaching hospital here in Toronto
وكنت مقيما في مستشفى تعليمي هنا في تورونتو
when Mrs. Drucker was brought to the emergency department
عندما أتت السيدة دراكر إلى قسم الطوارئ
of the hospital where I was working.
في المستشفى التي كنت اعمل بها.
At the time I was assigned to the cardiology service
في ذلك الوقت كنت معين لخدمة أمراض القلب
on a cardiology rotation.
على تناوب أمراض القلب.
And it was my job,
وكان عملي,
when the emergency staff called for a cardiology consult,
عندما يطلب موظفي الطوارئ مستشار أمراض القلب,
and to report back to my attending.
وتقديم تقرير للمسؤول.
And I saw Mrs. Drucker, and she was breathless.
رأيت السيدة دروكر لاهثه.
And when I listened to her, she was making a wheezy sound.
وعندما استمعت اليها, سمعتها تقوم بأصوات صافره.
And when I listened to her chest with a stethoscope,
وعندما كنت استمع الى صدرها بسماعة الطبيب،
I could hear crackly sounds on both sides
وكنت أسمع أصوات مكسره على الجانبين
that told me that she was in congestive heart failure.
وعرفت حينها انها تعاني من فشل القلب الاحتقاني.
This is a condition in which the heart fails,
هذة هي الحالة التي يفشل فيها القلب,
and instead of being able to pump all the blood forward,
وبدلاً من ان يضخ الدم الى الامام,
some of the blood backs up into the lung, the lungs fill up with blood,
بعض القلب يرجع الى اعلى الرئة، والرئتين تملأ بالدم،
and that's why you have shortness of breath.
لهذا السبب يكون لديك ضيق في التنفس.
And that wasn't a difficult diagnosis to make.
وذلك لم يكن يصعب تشخيصه.
I made it and I set to work treating her.
صنعته وظبطه ليتم علاجها.
I gave her aspirin. I gave her medications to relieve the strain on her heart.
اعطيتها أسبرين. اعطيتها ادويه لتخفيف الضغط على قلبها.
I gave her medications that we call diuretics, water pills,
أعطيتها الأدوية التي نسميها مدرات البول,
to get her to pee out the access fluid.
لتساعدها على التخلص من السوائل الزائدة (البول)
And over the course of the next hour and a half or two,
على مدار الساعة القادمة والنصف او الساعتين,
And I felt really good.
وأسعدني ذلك.
And that's when I made my first mistake;
وذلك عندما قمت بأول خطأ;
I sent her home.
ارسلتها الى المنزل.
Actually, I made two more mistakes.
في الواقع, قمت بخطأئين.
I sent her home
ارسلتها الى المنزل
without speaking to my attending.
دون ان اتكلم مع المسؤول.
I didn't pick up the phone and do what I was supposed to do,
لم ارفع سماعة التلفون ولم افعل ماكان يجب ان افعله,
which was call my attending and run the story by him
وهو اخبار المسؤول وترك القصه له
And he knew her,
وهو يعرفها
he would have been able to furnish additional information about her.
كان يمكنه تقديم معلومات إضافية عنها.
Maybe I did it for a good reason.
ربما فعلت ذلك لسبب جيد.
Maybe I didn't want to be a high-maintenance resident.
او ربما لم ارغب ان اكون مقيم مكلف.
Maybe I wanted to be so successful
ربما اردت ان اكون ناجحاً جداً
and so able to take responsibility
وقادر على تحمل المسؤولية
that I would do so
التي يمكنني ان اقوم بها
and I would be able to take care of my attending's patients
ويمكنني ان ارعى نزلاء صاحب المشفى
without even having to contact him.
دون الرجوع اليه.
The second mistake that I made was worse.
الخطأ الثاني الذي قمت به كان اسوأ.
In sending her home,
تمثّل في ارسالها الى المنزل,
I disregarded a little voice deep down inside
حيث انني تجاهلت صوت بداخلي
that was trying to tell me,
كان يحاول ان يخبرني,
"Goldman, not a good idea. Don't do this."
"قولدمان, ليست فكره جيدة, لا تفعلها."
In fact, so lacking in confidence was I
في الحقيقة, قلة في الثقة, انني
that I actually asked the nurse
قمت بسؤال الممرضة
who was looking after Mrs. Drucker,
"التي كانت تعتني بالسيدة درانكر,
"Do you think it's okay if she goes home?"
"هل تعتقدي انها ستكون بخير ان ذهبت الى المنزل؟"
And the nurse thought about it
والممرضة فكرت في الامر
and said very matter-of-factly, "Yeah, I think she'll do okay."
وقالت امراً وقعاً, "ستكون على مايرام."
I can remember that like it was yesterday.
اذكر ذلك وكانه وقع بالامس.
So I signed the discharge papers,
بهذا قمت بتوقيع اوراق الخروج,
and an ambulance came, paramedics came to take her home.
وجاءت سيارت الاسعاف, المسعفين واخذوها لمنزلها.
And I went back to my work on the wards.
وعدت انا لعملي في العنابر.
All the rest of that day,
كل بقية ذلك اليوم,
that afternoon,
ذلك الظهر,
I had this kind of gnawing feeling inside my stomach.
كنت احس شعوراً مزعج بمعدتي.
But I carried on with my work.
لكنني واصلت في عملي.
And at the end of the day, I packed up to leave the hospital
في نهاية الدوام, استعديت لمغادرة المستشفى
and walked to the parking lot
وذهبت الى موقف السيارات
to take my car and drive home
لاخذ سيارتي والذهاب الى المنزل
when I did something that I don't usually do.
عندما قمت بفعل شيء لا افعله عادةً.
I walked through the emergency department on my way home.
ذهبت من خلال قسم الطوارئ في طريقي الى المنزل.
And it was there that another nurse,
وكانت هنالك, تلك الممرضة,
not the nurse who was looking after Mrs. Drucker before, but another nurse,
ليست الممرضة التي كانت تعتني بالسيدة دانكر من قبل, ولكنها ممرضة اخرى,
that are the three words
الثلاثة كلمات
that most emergency physicians I know dread.
التي يخشاها اطباء الطواري,
Others in medicine dread them as well,
اخرون في الطب يخشونها ايضاً,
but there's something particular about emergency medicine
ولكن هناك شيء بالخصوص طب الطواري
The three words are:
الثلاثة كلمات هي:
Do you remember?
هل تذكر؟
"Do you remember that patient you sent home?"
"هل تذكر المريضه التي ارسلتها الى المنزل؟"
the other nurse asked matter-of-factly.
الممرضة الأخرى سألت امر واقع.
"Well she's back,"
"لقد عادت,"
in just that tone of voice.
في تلك اللهجه من الصوت.
Well she was back all right.
وقد عادت فعلا
She was back and near death.
عادت وكانت قريبة من الموت.
About an hour after she had arrived home,
مايقارب الساعة بعد رجوعها الى المنزل,
after I'd sent her home,
بعد ان ارسلتها الى المنزل,
she collapsed and her family called 911
انهارت فاتصلت اسرتها بـ 911
and the paramedics brought her back to the emergency department
والمسعفين ارجعوها الى قسم الطواري
where she had a blood pressure of 50,
كان لديها ضغط دم بلغ 50,
which is in severe shock.
وهو حالة صدمة شديدة.
And she was barely breathing and she was blue.
كانت تتنفس بصعوبة ولونها ازرق.
And the emerg. staff pulled out all the stops.
قام موظفي الطواري بسحب كل العقبات.
They gave her medications to raise her blood pressure.
اعطوها ادوية لترفع ضغط الدم.
They put her on a ventilator.
وضعوها على جهاز التنفس الصناعي.
And I was shocked
كنت مصدوماً
and shaken to the core.
ومرتجفا حتى النخاع.
And I went through this roller coaster,
تجاوزت هذا الدوران,
because after they stabilized her,
لانه بعد ان ساعدوها بالاستقرار,
she went to the intensive care unit,
ذهبت الى وحدة العناية المركزة,
and I hoped against hope that she would recover.
وكنت آمل على ان تتعافى.
And over the next two or three days,
خلال يومين او ثلاثة ايام,
it was clear that she was never going to wake up.
كان واضح انها لن تستيقظ مجدداً.
She had irreversible brain damage.
لديها ضرر دائم في المخ.
And the family gathered.
اجتمع اهلها.
And over the course of the next eight or nine days,
خلال ثمانية او تسعة ايام,
they resigned themselves to what was happening.
استسلموا لما سيحدُث.
And at about the nine day mark, they let her go --
وفي خلال تسعة ايام تركوها تذهب --
Mrs. Drucker,
السيدة دانكر,
a wife, a mother
زوجة, أم
and a grandmother.
وجدة.
They say you never forget the names
يقال انك ابدا لن تنسى أسماء
of those who die.
الذين يموتون.
And that was my first time to be acquainted with that.
وكانت المرة الاولى التي تعرفت فيها على ذلك.
Over the next few weeks,
وبعد بضع اسابيع,
I beat myself up
قمت بضرب نفسي
and I experienced for the first time
وشعرت لأول مرة
the unhealthy shame that exists
بالعار الموجود
in our culture of medicine --
في ثقافتنا الطبية --
where I felt alone, isolated,
حيث شعرت بانني وحيد, معزول,
not feeling the healthy kind of shame that you feel,
ليس شعور العار الطبيعي الذي تشعر به,
because you can't talk about it with your colleagues.
لانك لا تستطيع التحدث به مع زملائك.
when you betray a secret that a best friend made you promise never to reveal
عندما تكشف سرا اخبرك صديقك ان لا تكشفه
and then your best friend confronts you
ثم يواجهك صديقك
and you have terrible discussions,
وتواجه مناقشة فظيعة,
but at the end of it all that sick feeling guides you
وفي النهاية الشعور المتعب يدلك
and you say, I'll never make that mistake again.
وتقول, لن افعل ذلك الخطأ مرة اخرى.
And you make amends and you never make that mistake again.
وتعوضه بأنك لن تقع في الخطأ مرة اخرى.
That's the kind of shame that is a teacher.
ذلك هو العار المعلم.
The unhealthy shame I'm talking about
العار الغير صحي الذي اتحدث عنه
is the one that makes you so sick inside.
هو الذي يتعب جداً من الداخل.
It's the one that says,
الذي يقول,
not that what you did was bad,
ليس ان مافعلته كان سيء,
but that you are bad.
ولكن انك انت سيء.
And it was what I was feeling.
وكان ذاك ما شعرت به
And it wasn't because of my attending; he was a doll.
ليس لأن المسؤول عني, كان أيقونة.
He talked to the family, and I'm quite sure that he smoothed things over
تحدث مع الاسرة, ومتأكد انه هدأ الامور
and made sure that I didn't get sued.
وتأكد انني لن اُحاكم.
And I kept asking myself these questions.
وكنت اسأل نفسي هذه الاسئلة.
Why didn't I ask my attending? Why did I send her home?
لماذا لن اسأل المسؤول؟ لماذا ارسلتها الى المنزل؟
And then at my worst moments:
وفي اسوأ اوقاتي:
Why did I make such a stupid mistake?
لماذا قمت بخطأ غبي؟
Why did I go into medicine?
لماذا درست الطب؟
Slowly but surely,
ببطء ولكن بتأكد,
it lifted.
تحسنت.
I began to feel a bit better.
بدأت اشعر بتحسن.
And on a cloudy day,
وفي يوم مليئ بالغيوم
there was a crack in the clouds and the sun started to come out
كان هناك شقوق في السحب ولكن الشمس بدأت بالخروج
maybe I could feel better again.
يمكن سأشعر بتحسن.
And I made myself a bargain
قمت بصفقة مع نفسي
that if only I redouble my efforts to be perfect
هذا لو ضاعفت جهدي لان اكون مثالياً
and never make another mistake again,
ولا ارتكب اي خطأ مرة اخرى,
please make the voices stop.
رجاءً اوقف الاصوات.
And they did.
وتوقفت.
And I went back to work.
ورجعت الى العمل.
And then it happened again.
ثم حدثت مرة اخرى.
Two years later I was an attending in the emergency department
بعد سنتين كنت مسؤولاً في قسم الطواري
at a community hospital just north of Toronto,
في مستشفى الحي في شمال تورنتو,
and I saw a 25 year-old man with a sore throat.
فرأيت رجلا يبلغ من العمر 25 عاماً مصاب بالتهاب الحلق.
It was busy, I was in a bit of a hurry.
كنت مشغولاً, كنت مسرعاً.
He kept pointing here.
ظل يشير الى هنا (حلقه).
I looked at his throat, it was a little bit pink.
نظرت الى حلقه, وجدته وردي قليلا.
And I gave him a prescription for penicillin
اعطيته روشته لبنسلين
and sent him on his way.
وارسلته في طريقه
And even as he was walking out the door,
وكان حينها متجهاً الى الباب,
he was still sort of pointing to his throat.
كان مازال يشير الى حلقه.
And two days later I came to do my next emergency shift,
وبعد يومين اتيت لاقوم بدوامي الثاني في الطواري,
and that's when my chief asked to speak to me quietly in her office.
وذلك عندما طلبت مني الرئيسه ان تتحدث الي بهدوء في مكتبها.
And she said the three words:
وقالت بضع كلمات:
Do you remember?
هل تذكر؟
"Do you remember that patient you saw with the sore throat?"
هل تذكر المريض الذي شخصته بالتهاب الحلق؟
Well it turns out, he didn't have a strep throat.
اتضح انه لم يكن يعاني ببكتيريا الحلق.
He had a potentially life-threatening condition
كان لديه حالة يحتمل ان تهدد حياته
You can Google it,
يمكنك بحثها في قوقل,
but it's an infection, not of the throat, but of the upper airway,
ولكنه التهاب, ليس في الحلق ولكنه في اعلى مجرى الهواء,
and it can actually cause the airway to close.
يمكن أن يتسبب في اغلاق مجرى الهواء.
And fortunately he didn't die.
لحسن الحظ لم يمت.
He was placed on intravenous antibiotics
تم وضعه على المضادات الحيوية عن طريق الوريد
and he recovered after a few days.
بعد بضع ايام تماثل للشفاء.
And I went through the same period of shame and recriminations
ومررت بنفس العار و تبادل الاتهامات
and felt cleansed and went back to work,
وشعرت بتحسن ورجعت الى العمل,
until it happened again and again and again.
حتى حدث مرارا وتكرارا وتكرارا.
Twice in one emergency shift, I missed appendicitis.
مرتين في دوام الطواري, فاتني التهاب الزائدة الدودية.
Now that takes some doing,
الان يتطلب بعض العمل,
especially when you work in a hospital
بالاخص عندما تعمل بمستشفى
that at the time saw but 14 people a night.
ترى فيها في الليلة الواحدة 14 شخصاً.
Now in both cases, I didn't send them home
في الحالتين, لم ارسلهم الى المنزل
and I don't think there was any gap in their care.
ولا أعتقد أن هناك أي فجوة في عنايتهم.
One I thought had a kidney stone.
واحد اعتقدت ان لديه حصوى في الكلى.
I ordered a kidney X-ray. When it turned out to be normal,
أمرت باشعة للكلى. ولكن اتضح انها عادية,
my colleague who was doing a reassessment of the patient
احد زملائي الذي كان يقوم بإعادة تقيم لمريض
noticed some tenderness in the right lower quadrant and called the surgeons.
لاحظ رقة في اسفل الربع الايمن فدعا الجراحين.
The other one had a lot of diarrhea.
الاخر كان مصاباً بالإسهال.
I ordered some fluids to rehydrate him
أمرت ببعض السوائل لترطيبه
and asked my colleague to reassess him.
وطلبت من احد الزملاء بمراجعته.
And he did
وفعل ذلك
and when he noticed some tenderness in the right lower quadrant, called the surgeons.
قام بطلب الجراحين عندما لاحظ ليونة في اسفل الربع الايمن.
In both cases,
في الحالتين,
they had their operations and they did okay.
اجرت لهم عمليات وكانوا بخير.
But each time,
لكن في كل مرة,
they were gnawing at me, eating at me.
كانوا متضايقين مني.
And I'd like to be able to say to you
وأود ان اكون قادرا باخباركم
that my worst mistakes only happened in the first five years of practice
ان اسوأ اخطائي كانت فقط في الخمسة سنين الاولى التجريبية
as many of my colleagues say, which is total B.S.
كما قال كثير من زملائي وهي ماتعادل بي اس
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Some of my doozies have been in the last five years.
بعض اضطراباتي كانت في الخمس سنين الاخيرة.
Alone, ashamed and unsupported.
وحيداً, خجولاً وبدون مشجع.
Here's the problem:
هنا المشكله:
If I can't come clean
أذا لم استطع ان أتي نظيفاً
and talk about my mistakes,
واتحدث عن اخطائي,
if I can't find the still-small voice
ان لم اجد الصوت الهادي
that tells me what really happened,
الذي يخبرني ماذا حدث,
how can I share it with my colleagues?
كيف لي ان اشارك به زملائي؟
How can I teach them about what I did
كيف اعلمهم عما فعلت
so that they don't do the same thing?
لكي لا يفعلوا نفس الشئ؟
If I were to walk into a room --
اذا دخلت الى غرفة
like right now, I have no idea what you think of me.
كالان, لا اعرف ماذا ستقولون عني.
When was the last time you heard somebody talk
متى كانت اخر مره سمعتم فيها شخصاً
about failure after failure after failure?
يتحدث عن خطأ تلى الاخر؟
Oh yeah, you go to a cocktail party
نعم, ستذهب الى حفل كوكتيل
and you might hear about some other doctor,
وربما ستسمع عن اطباء اخرون
but you're not going to hear somebody
لكنك لن تسمع احد
talking about their own mistakes.
يتحدث عن اخطاءه.
If I were to walk into a room filled with my colleages
اذا دخلت الى غرفة ملئية بزملائي
and ask for their support right now
وطلبت مساندتهم لي الان
and start to tell what I've just told you right now,
وبدأت اخبرهم بنفس ما اخبرتكم به
I probably wouldn't get through two of those stories
لا اعتقد اني كنت سأمر بهذين القصتين
before they would start to get really uncomfortable,
قبل ان يشعرون بعدم الارتياح,
they'd change the subject and we would move on.
سيقومون بتغير الموضوع.
And in fact, if I knew and my colleagues knew
في الحقيقة لو كنت اعرف وزملائي يعرفون
that one of my orthopedic colleagues took off the wrong leg in my hospital,
ان احد اطباء العظام قام بخلع رجل بالخطأ في المستشفى المسؤول عنها,
believe me, I'd have trouble
صدقوني, سأكون في ورطه
making eye contact with that person.
حين اقابل ذلك الطبيب.
That's the system that we have.
هذا هو نظامنا.
It's a complete denial of mistakes.
حرمان كامل من الاخطاء.
It's a system
هو النظام
in which there are two kinds of physicians --
الذي يوجد به نوعان من المواقف --
those who make mistakes
الذين يُخطئون
and those who don't,
والذين لا يُخطئون,
those who can't handle sleep deprivation and those who can,
الذين لا يستطيعون الامتناع عن النوم والذين يستطيعون,
those who have lousy outcomes
الذين لديهم نتائج رديئه
and those who have great outcomes.
والذين لديهم نتائج جيدة.
And it's almost like an ideological reaction,
وهي تقريبا ردة فعل فكريه
like the antibodies begin to attack that person.
مثل الأجسام المضادة تبدأ في مهاجمة الشخص.
And we have this idea
ولدينا فكرة
that if we drive the people who make mistakes
لو قمنا بدفع الذين يُخطئون
out of medicine,
خارج الطب,
what will we be left with, but a safe system.
ماذا سيتبقى لنا, غير نظام امن.
But there are two problems with that.
يوجد مشكلتين بذلك.
In my 20 years or so
خلال الـ 20 عاما
of medical broadcasting and journalism,
من العمل في اذاعة وصحافة طبية ,
I've made a personal study of medical malpractice and medical errors
قمت بدراسة شخصية عن سوء الممارسة والاخطاء الطبية
to learn everything I can,
لأتعلم كل ما استطيع,
from one of the first articles I wrote for the Toronto Star
من اول المقالات التي كتبتها في صحيفة تورنتو استار
And what I've learned
وماتعلمته
is that errors are absolutely ubiquitous.
الأخطاء موجودة في كل مكان على الاطلاق.
We work in a system
نعمل في نظام
where errors happen every day,
تحدث الاخطاء فيه كل يوم,
where one in 10 medications
في واحد من كل 10 ادوية
are either the wrong medication given in hospital
اما الدواء اعطى بالخطأ من قبل المستشفى
or at the wrong dosage,
او خطأ في الجرعة,
where hospital-acquired infections are getting more and more numerous,
حيث تنتشر العدوى التي تصيب داخل المستشفيات باعداد كبيرة متزايدة,
causing havoc and death.
تؤدي الى الخسائر والموت.
In this country,
في هذا البلد,
as many as 24,000 Canadians die
ما يصل الى 24,000 كندي يموتون
of preventable medical errors.
بسبب الأخطاء الطبية التي لربما امكن تفاديها.
In the United States, the Institute of Medicine pegged it at 100,000.
في الولايات المتحدة, قدّر معهد الطب عدد 100,000.
In both cases, these are gross underestimates,
في الحالتين هذا تقليل من الاجمالي,
because we really aren't ferreting out the problem
لأننا لا نتحرى المشكله
as we should.
كما ينبغي لنا
And here's the thing.
وهنا تكمن الفكرة.
In a hospital system
في نظام المستشفى
where medical knowledge is doubling
حيث المعرفة الطبية مضاعفة
every two or three years, we can't keep up with it.
كل سنتين او ثلاثة, لا نستطيع مواكبتها.
Sleep deprivation is absolutely pervasive.
قلة النوم متشرة كليا
We can't get rid of it.
لا نستطيع التخلص منها.
We have our cognitive biases,
لدينا تحيزات معرفية,
so that I can take a perfect history on a patient with chest pain.
بحيث انني استطيع اخذ تاريخ ممتاز للمريض في اَلام الصدر.
Now take the same patient with chest pain,
الان خذ نفس المريض بالام الصدر,
make them moist and garrulous
اجعلها رطبة
and put a little bit of alcohol on their breath,
وضع قليل من الكحول في انفاسه,
and suddenly my history is laced with contempt.
وفجأة تاريخي ارتبط بالخزي.
I don't take the same history.
لا اخذ نفس التاريخ.
I'm not a robot;
انا لست إنسان آلي,
I don't do things the same way each time.
لا أفعل الأشياء بنفس الطريقة في كل مرة.
And my patients aren't cars;
مرضاي ليسو سيارات;
they don't tell me their symptoms in the same way each time.
لا يقولون نفس الاعراض بنفس الطريقة في كل مرة.
Given all of that, mistakes are inevitable.
مع كل ذلك, الأخطاء أمر لا مفر منه.
So if you take the system, as I was taught,
لذلك لو اخذت النظام, بالطريقة التي دُرّستُ بها,
and weed out all the error-prone health professionals,
و تخلصت من كل من يقوم باخطاء طبية,
well there won't be anybody left.
حينها لن يبقى اي شخص.
And you know that business
هل تعرفون عن ذلك المجال
about people not wanting
عن اناس لا يريدون
to talk about their worst cases?
ان يتحدثوا عن اسوأ الإحتمالات؟
On my show, on "White Coat, Black Art,"
في برنامجي, "المعطف الابيض, الفن الاسود,"
I made it a habit of saying, "Here's my worst mistake,"
اصبحت عادتي ان اقول, "ها هي اسوأ اخطائي,"
from paramedics to the chief of cardiac surgery,
من المسعفين إلى رئيس جراحة القلب،
"Here's my worst mistake," blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
"ها هي اسوأ اخطائي," كذا وكذا وكذا وكذا وكذا،
"What about yours?" and I would point the microphone towards them.
"ماذا عنك؟" وأود ان اشير المايكرفون عليهم.
And their pupils would dilate,
وتلاميذهم يتمددون,
they would recoil,
يتراجعون,
then they would look down and swallow hard
ثم ينظرون الى الاسفل ويبتلعون بصعوبه
and start to tell me their stories.
والبدء بروي قصصهم.
They want to tell their stories. They want to share their stories.
يريدون أن يرووا قصصهم. يريدون المشاركه بقصصهم.
They want to be able to say,
يريدون ان يكونوا قادرين على قول,
"Look, don't make the same mistake I did."
"انظر, لا تفعل نفس الخطأ الذي قمت به انا."
What they need is an environment to be able to do that.
مايحتاجونه هو بيئه يستطيعون ان يفعلوا فيها ذلك.
And it starts with one physician at a time.
يبدأ مع طبيب واحد في الوقت الواحد.
The redefined physician is human,
اعادة تعريف الطبيب بأنه انسان,
knows she's human,
تعرف انها انسان,
accepts it, isn't proud of making mistakes,
تقبلها, ليست فخورة باخطائها,
but strives to learn one thing
لكنها تحاول تعلم شيء واحد
from what happened
من الذي حدث
that she can teach to somebody else.
لتعلمه لشخص اخر.
She shares her experience with others.
تشارك بتجاربها مع الاخرين.
She's supportive when other people talk about their mistakes.
تساند الاخرين عندما يتحدثون عن اخطائهم.
And she points out other people's mistakes,
وتشير لاخطاء الاخرين,
not in a gotcha way,
ليس بسخرية
but in a loving, supportive way
ولكن بحب, ومسانده
so that everybody can benefit.
ليستفيد منها الجميع.
And she works in a culture of medicine
وتعمل في الثقافة الطبية
that acknowledges
وتفهم
that human beings run the system,
ان الانسان هو الذي يشغل النظام,
and when human beings run the system, they will make mistakes from time to time.
وعندما يشغل الانسان النظام, سيقوم بفعل اخطاء من وقت لأخر.
to create backups
لإنشاء نسخ احتياطية
that make it easier to detect those mistakes
لتسهيل الكشف عن الاخطاء
that humans inevitably make
بأن الانسان يكرر
and also fosters in a loving, supportive way
وايضاً يشجع بحب, ومساندة
places where everybody who is observing
اماكن يستطيع كل من يراقب فيها
in the health care system
نظام الرعاية الصحية
can actually point out things that could be potential mistakes
ان يشير للامور التي يحتمل فيها الاخطاء
and is rewarded for doing so,
وان يكافأ للقيام بذلك،
and especially people like me, when we do make mistakes,
وخصوصاً اشخاصاً مثلي, يرتكبون اخطاء,
My name is Brian Goldman.
اسمي براين قولدمان.
I am a redefined physician.
انا طبيب معاد التعريف.
I'm human. I make mistakes.
انا انسان, اقوم بأخطاء.
I'm sorry about that,
اسف لذلك,
but I strive to learn one thing
ولكنني اسعى لتعلم شيء واحد
that I can pass on to other people.
بامكاني نقله لاشخاص اخرين
I still don't know what you think of me,
مازلت لا اعرف رايكم في شخصي,
but I can live with that.
لكنني استطيع العيش مع ذلك.
And let me close with three words of my own:
اتركوني اختم بثلاثة كلمات مني:
I do remember.
انا فعلاً أتذكر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)